<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to divers scandals mentioned in a certain pamphlet, entituled, The humble remonstrance of Sr. Iohn Stawell. Written by John Ashe Esquire, 1654.</title>
            <author>Ashe, John, Esquire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1072_2*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867191</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867191</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1072[2*], 249:E1072[2*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to divers scandals mentioned in a certain pamphlet, entituled, The humble remonstrance of Sr. Iohn Stawell. Written by John Ashe Esquire, 1654.</title>
                  <author>Ashe, John, Esquire.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Newcomb, dwelling in Thamestreet, over against Baynards Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Domini 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An answer to Stawell, John.  To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers: the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stawell, John, --  Sir, 1599-1662. --  To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers: the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confiscation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO DIVERS SCANDALS Mentioned in a certain <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> Entituled, THE Humble Remonſtrance OF S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> IOHN STAWELL.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By <hi>JOHN ASHE</hi> Eſquire, 1654.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Thameſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynards</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:170632:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170632:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO Divers <hi>Scandals</hi> mentioned in a certain <hi>PAMPHLET,</hi> Entituled, THE Humble Remonſtrance OF Sir John Stawell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not my purpoſe at this time, to write an exact Narrative of all proceedings and paſſages which have been in the Caſe of Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> from the 18 of <hi>July</hi> 1646. which was the time of his firſt coming to <hi>London</hi> from <hi>Exceter,</hi> unto the year 1652. at which time he was Arraigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the High Court of Juſtice; I having done that formerly even upon the firſt ſight of that Scandalous Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>The Humble Remonſtrance of Sir John Stawell;</hi> but did not at that time expoſe it to publique view for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Becauſe an Anſwer had been given by me to all thoſe Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars which may any way ſeem to reflect on me before the High-Court of Juſtice, to the general ſatisfaction of the whole Court, and all that were preſent, and to the ſhame and confuſion of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> who was then a Priſoner at the Barr of the ſaid Court.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Becauſe the Scandals mentioned in the ſaid Pamphlet, were ſo apparently falſe and improbable, that any one who hath been in the leaſt manner acquainted with thoſe tranſactions, might eaſily perceive,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170632:3"/> even in the ſaid Paper, a manifeſt confutation of thoſe falſhoods, which are therein malitiouſly ſuggeſted, and vainly charged on me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Becauſe that in regard of my reſpects to his Family, I was willing to be ſilent, leſt in giving an Anſwer to thoſe ſcandals, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he endeavoureth in the ſaid Pamphlet to aſperſe me (by ſaying that I did clandeſtinely obſtruct his compoſition) I ſhould do what I conceive my ſelf at this time obliged unto (viz.) clearly prove by undeniable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and circumſtances, that he never intended to compound at all, but reſolved on the contrary, flattering himſelf with hopes of ſeeing the late King reſtored to his Power and greatneſs, from whom he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not only his whole Eſtate, (which was unjuſtly taken from him, as he conſtantly affirmed) but alſo a great reward for his many ſufferings in owning and defending the Cauſe of the ſaid King, beyond any of his Party.</p>
            <p>But ſince the Honourable Parliament hath been pleaſed to refer the Petition of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> unto a Committee, where the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact may be throughly examined, to the end that my teſtimony on the behalf of the Commonwealth, may not ſeem to be any way im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, in regard of thoſe feigned Scandals mentioned in his ſaid Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, and leſt my carriage in the buſineſs of his Compoſition, might be miſrepreſented to thoſe who were ſtrangers to my actions therein,</p>
            <p>I have judged it neceſſary to publiſh theſe enſuing lines, premiſing a few Particulars which were fully cleared in that diſcourſe, which I did then write, which are as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That although Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> did appear at the Committee of Gold-Smiths Hall, about four daies before the time limited by the Articles of <hi>Exceter</hi> for Compoſitions were expired, yet he never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make any Compoſition there according to the Order of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Rules preſcribed for Compoſition upon the ſaid Articles, but did oftentimes declare his reſolution to the contrary: And when the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> his wife, and Sir <hi>Edward Stawell</hi> his ſon then in <hi>France,</hi> did earneſtly ſolicite him, that they, or either of them, might Petition the Parliament to be admitted to compound for the ſaid Eſtate, ſince he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it; Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> did deny to give his conſent thereunto, and did threaten his ſaid ſon, that in caſe he did attempt any ſuch thing, he would diſinherit him; and was much incenſed againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Edward Stawell,</hi> for that he had written Letters unto Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> for his admiſſion to Compoſition, ſince his Father refuſed it; ſome of which Letters Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> intercepted.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did wholly depend upon the late Kings reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to his power and authority, that from him he might receive not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his whole eſtate, (then unjuſtly taken from him by the Parliament, as he ſaid) but alſo a great reward for his many ſufferings, in owning and juſtifying the late Kings Cauſe beyond any other of his party; and did ſend to the ſaid King when he was laſt at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, deſiring him to take notice of the great ſuffering he had undergone for his Majeſties Cauſe: and did let him know the hopes he had of his Majeſties great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, and reward when he ſhould be reſtored.</p>
            <p>And upon this confidence did Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> neglect his compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and refuſed the benefit of Exceter Articles.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170632:3"/> 3. That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> during the life of the late King, and after his firſt appearance at Goldſmiths Hall, did never tender any Petition for his admittance to compoſition, or to claim the benefit of Exceter Articles, either unto the Parliament or Committee of Parliament, or any other Court whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And when in the life time of the late King, he was arraigned for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the Upper Bench Bar, he did not then claim the benefit of Exceter Articles, nor made any mention of them; for his exemption from that tryal: but on the contrary, he not onely refuſed to own the Judge that ſat there, by Commiſſion from the Parliament; but uttered an expreſſion to the Court to this, or the like effect, <hi>viz.</hi> My offence is not Treaſon, for which I am here arraigned; but becauſe I would not permit the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Goldſmiths Hall to pick my purſe, and give my conſent to pay a ſum of money for the redemption of my Eſtate, which is unjuſtly taken from me: by which expreſſion, he ſufficiently declared his reſolution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt compounding.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That I did with all reallity and faithfulneſs, uſe my utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to perſwade Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to ſubmit unto the Parliament, and to make his Compoſition; that ſo himſelf and his poſterity might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from ruine: and that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did refuſe to follow that my councel and advice, and did declare that his reſolution was not to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, but to depend upon the ſaid Kings favour.</p>
            <p>And when I did preſs him to follow the examples of all the other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Kings Party who ſubmitted to Compoſition, he did ſeem to jeer and deride them for their follies, intimating that his Eſtate would be reſtored him by the King, with ſufficient damages from thoſe that had poſſeſſed the ſame during the Sequeſtration; and for that reaſon would not permit either his Lady, or any other friend for her, to take any of his Eſtate at a Rent from the Sequeſtrators.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That thoſe ſcandalous aſperſions caſt upon me by Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in his Pamphlet, Entituled his <hi>Humble Remonſtrance,</hi> and menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in page 23, 24, 28, and 30. are meer fictions, and never heard of by me, or any other perſon that I could ever meet withall, untill the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had ordered Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to be tryed by a High Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and had required me to attend the ſaid Court, as a Witneſs againſt him. And I do believe that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> did frame and contrive thoſe falſe and ſcandalous fictions, after the death of the late King, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereby to ſave his reputation, and to excuſe his wilfull perverſneſs; thereby endeavouring to make the world believe that it was not his own madneſs and folly that had brought him to ruine; but the treachery of a friend, upon whom he relyed: And this is one reaſon, as I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that thoſe fictions were printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly, That in caſe I ſhould at any time hinder Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi>'s Compoſition; nay, if I had not endeavoured to the utmoſt of my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to perſwade him to the ſame, I might deſervedly be cenſured to be guilty of as much madneſs and folly, as he now lyeth under for not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
            <p>For that the Parliament had Ordered Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Compoſition-money, with the Compoſitions of Mr. <hi>Coventry,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Moſeley,</hi> to be paid unto me for the diſcharge of ſeveral disburſments
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170632:4"/> and engagements which I had paid and entred into, together with Col. <hi>Alexander Popham,</hi> Col. <hi>Nathaniel Fines,</hi> Col. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> for the ſervice of the Parliament, and paying of their Forces; and by the ſaid Order, I was to receive ſome ſatisfaction out of the ſaid Compoſitions, towards my great loſs and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſuſtained by the late War; but Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> not compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thoſe debts, disburſments, and engagements, are not all ſatisfied and paid, nor have I received any ſatisfaction towards my ſaid loſs and dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by which means I and the other Gentlemen above mentioned, have and will ſuffer very much, in caſe the Parliament do not diſcharge thoſe obligations ſtill in force.</p>
            <p>And I in particular do loſe at leaſt five thouſand pound, for that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> did not make his Compoſition, for that his Compoſition amounted unto ſeven or eight thouſand pound, or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many other particulars are ſet forth, plainly manifeſted, and clearly proved, in the Treatiſe which I did then write, as is above mentioned; but in regard the Book proves to be of ſo large a volume that it will require much time in the Printing thereof, and if Printed, thoſe Honorable Perſons to whom Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> hath directed his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, will want time, as I conceive, to read the ſame. I have therefore for theſe and the other reaſons firſt given, and in the beginning of this Treatiſe expreſſed, contracted the matter, and only printed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the preſent in anſwer to what is contained in the pages 28 and 30 of Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> Pamphlet, Entituled, his <hi>Humble Remonſtrance,</hi> and is as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>READER,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Page of the ſaid humble Remonſtrance of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> he doth engage the Faith of a Chriſtian, and honour of a Gentleman, to declare and Remonſtrate his Caſe in all humility and truth: In anſwer to which, I may with confidence affirm, and do preſume, that the enſuing diſcourſe will clearly prove the ſame; that if his actings in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> and his dealings with the people of <hi>Taunton,</hi> be as truly declared and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as thoſe paſſages ſet down in Page 23. 24. 28. &amp; 30. concerning his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes &amp; proceeding with my ſelf, that then there is not ſcarce one line of truth in the whole narrative: for I do ſay and affirm, that the whole relation contained in Pages 23. 24. 28. and 30. is a falſe and ſcandalous aſperſion, and a fiction invented and contrived by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſince the death of the late King, for the ends and reaſons before mentioned; and becauſe the matters contained in pages 28. and 30. do ſeem moſt to reflect upon my reputation, and are more notoriouſly ſcandalous then the reſt: I am reſolved at this time to give an Anſwer only to thoſe, and the rather becauſe the paſſages contained in pages 23. and 24. relating to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi>'s appearance at Goldſmiths Hall, his miſcarriages there, and the report thereof made to the Parliament will be examined, and at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared before the Committee, now appointed to examine the ſame.</p>
            <p>Reader, if thou ſhalt ſeriouſly peruſe, what is ſet forth by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in page 28. thou maieſt eaſily perceive, that his deſign is to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate theſe particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> being put into a little dark corner, where
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170632:4"/> he was kept from nine of the clock in the morning, till three in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and no man ſuffered to come to him but Mr. <hi>Aſhe,</hi> and that then Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> reſorted to him four or five times, during his abode in that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle dark corner.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that whilſt Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was in the ſaid dark Corner, Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did treat with him about the purchaſe of his Farme at Abery, and did offer to give four thouſand pound for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that ſome few dayes before Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was put into the ſaid dark corner, Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> had diſcourſe with him about the ſale of his Fee-ſimple lands to pay his compoſition.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> having diſcovered his deſire to buy the Farm of Abery, he was ſharply reproved for the ſame by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe four particulars are plainly ſet down, and with convenient bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs affirmed in this Paragraph. Unto all which I ſhall in the firſt place make this generall Anſwer, and for the proof of it I have more then one hundred witneſſes: Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> being brought before the High Court of Juſtice in Weſtminſter Hall; and I being then preſent as a witneſs by order of Parliament: Mr. Atturny General was pleaſed, to acquaint the Court that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> (at his firſt appearance there, when Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> was abſent) had caſt out ſome words of reflection againſt him, and had likewiſe filled the Town with reports of the great matters he had to charge Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> with all, if ever he appeared in that Court: Whereupon the ſaid Atturny General did pray the Court, that ſince Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> was there preſent, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> might openly declare what he had to charge Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> withall; which motion the Court approved of, and thereupon wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to ſpeak what he had to ſay; Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condeſended to what the Court had approved of upon Mr. Atturnies motion; and then related ſeveral headleſs ſtories, fictions of his own brain; and when he had ſaid all, Mr. Attorny told the Court that he did believe, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had much more to ſay, for that which he had then ſpoken did not any way reflect upon <hi>Mr. Aſhe,</hi> nor anſwer the reports he had ſpread about the Town; wherefore the Attorny General preſſed Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> again and again to ſpeak all that he had to ſay; and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> then ſaid he had ſpoken all: Then the Lord Preſident of that Court ſpake unto Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to this effect. Sir, the Court with much patience hath heard you tell a long ſtory, though nothing at all to your buſineſs that is before us; the ſubſtance of which you have now ſaid, is only this: That Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did adviſe you to ſell your Farm at Abery, and with that money to pay your compoſition; did he, or any for him treat with you to buy the ſame, or did he diſcover any deſire he had to buy the Farm at Abery of you?</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> anſwered no my Lord he did not; how then ſaid the Lord Preſident can this ſtory of yours reflect upon Mr. <hi>Aſhe.</hi> Yes ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> for I do think or believe, that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did intend to buy the Farm, becauſe he did adviſe me to ſell it.</p>
            <p>This being the truth of all that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had then to accuſe me of; as to the purchaſe of the Farm of Abery, the Reader may plainly perceive, that then he had not fully contrived the fiction and Scandal now printed in his Remonſtrance. But let us now farther examine the particulars; Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> in that part of the Paragraph from whence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170632:5"/> the firſt particulars above mentioned is taken, hath ſo pen'd the ſame, as if the Reader ſhould conceive, that the Serjeant at Arms attending the Parliament, had by direction from me placed Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in that little dark place, that ſo I might with the more privacy treat about the pretended purchaſe; when as I did not know where the Serjeant had put him, or did know that little dark Corner, as the Serjeant can and will teſtifie.</p>
            <p>That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was kept in that little dark Corner, from nine of the Clock in the morning, till three of the Clock in the afternoon, and no man permitted to ſpeak with him but my ſelf, is that which I can give no anſwer unto; but I do believe that the Serjeant at Arms, who put Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> into that place can and will teſtifie the contrary.</p>
            <p>But that I did reſort unto Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> whilſt he was in that dark place four or five times is a notorious untruth, and a contrivance to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the remainder, <hi>viz.</hi> the grand fiction; for beſides the teſtimony of the Serjeant at Arms, who knows the contrary. Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> towards the end of this Paragraph faith, that after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as he pretends) I was ſoundly reproved for attempting to purchaſe the Farm of Abery; I then left him, which was about a quarter of an hour before he was called to the Bar of the Parliament. Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> doth not ſay that I came unto him again, whilſt he was in that dark Corner, nor can the ingenious Reader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that after Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> had received ſuch an angry reprehenſion from Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> for attempting that purchaſe, he would reſort unto him any more upon that errand; therefore it muſt be underſtood, that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> reſorted unto Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> into that dark Corner 4 or 5 times between the hours of 10 and 11; for I do affirm and believe that the Serjeant at Arms, beſides many other perſons do yet well remember,</p>
            <p>That it was 10 of the Clock when the Serjeant firſt gave notice to the Speaker, that he had cauſed Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to be brought, and that he was at the door to attend the pleaſure of the Houſe; and that at or before 11 of the Clock Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was called into the Houſe, and from thence ordered to Newgate.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond part of this Paragraph, where Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſaith, that ſome few dayes before he was brought to the Parliament, and put into that dark Corner; Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> had ſome diſcourſe with him about the ſale of his Fee-ſimple lands, to pay his compoſition: I do give this anſwer, that the ſame in every particle is an abſolute untruth; for that neither a few daies before, or at any time in all my life, had I any ſuch diſcourſe with Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I do now adviſe Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> that in caſe he ſhall print another Remonſtrance, to imploy his invention to find out the place where, and the time when, the aforeſaid diſcourſe was between us; and certainly he muſt then contrive it, as if it had been in ſome unknown place in <hi>Eutopia</hi> for it was never ſpoken in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath ſaved us the labour, to enquire further after the time when the ſaid diſcourſe ſhould be between us; for he tells us in the very ſame page, that this diſcourſe was when Deans and Chapters Lands were ſet to ſale for 10 years purchaſe; which was in the year 1649. and in the year 1646 when this diſcourſe is pretended to be; both Houſes of Parliament had then ſetled the Deans and Chapters Lands, for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170632:5"/> encreaſe of the Miniſters Maintenance, and the Schollers in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and thoſe Lands were never put to ſale untill the year 1649. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> muſt here be put in mind of the old Proverb (which in civil Engliſh ſignifies thus much) That, A good Memory is needfull to thoſe who ſhall frame feigned diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe two other particulars drawn from this Paragraph <hi>(viz.)</hi> That Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> ſhould Treat with Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> about the Purchaſe of his Farm of <hi>Aubery,</hi> and offered for the ſame 4000<hi>l.</hi> And that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſhould ſharply reprehend him for this Treaty and Offer, which is the grand fiction, and principal ground work upon which all his other Stories are raiſed, I can give no other anſwer thereunto, than what I have given to the former Accuſations: Which is, That I never had any ſuch Treaty with Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> or did offer him the ſaid Sum of 4000<hi>l.</hi> and I have no leſs number of Witneſſes to make good this my Affirmation, then all thoſe Honorable Judges who ſate at the High-Court of Juſtice, and thoſe Gentlemen who were at the ſame time preſent, when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did there relate this ſtory, as is aforſaid at large recited.</p>
            <p>And now to the end the ingenious Reader may rightly underſtand, and be truely informed upon what unjuſt grounds Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath made this great noiſe, and caſt theſe falſe aſperſions upon me; and that the world may behold the ſlender twigg which this prudent, yet wilfull and obſtinate Gentleman hath catched at, to ſave himſelf, his eſtate, and loſt reputation, from an abſolute ſinking, is one end of this preſent Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>I ſhall in the next place ſet down, and give the Reader a true, faithfull, and exact Narative of all that was ſaid and done by me, at the time when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was brought to the Parliament-Houſe, and put into that little dark corner, as he is pleaſed to call it: Which is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>Upon the 18 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1646. about nine of the clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (prayers being ended, and the Parliament ſate) Mr. <hi>Iohn Stevens</hi> took the firſt oportunity to acquaint the Speaker, that he was ordered by the Committee at Gold-Smiths Hall, to report to the Houſe the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent behaviour and miſcarriage of one Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> that came there under a pretence of a Compounder, That the Committee of Gold-Smiths Hall had delivered the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to the cuſtody of the Serjeant at Arms, that ſo he might be forth-coming, to anſwer that Charge which he ſhould then give againſt him; and therefore did move that the ſaid Serjeant at Arms might be ordered to bring Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to the Barr of the Houſe, to hear the Charge which ſhould be delivered againſt him in his ſaid Report. And the Parliament did then order the Serjeant to ſend for Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> from <hi>Ely</hi> Houſe accordingly; which done, the Houſe fell upon the Debate of other Buſineſs, which took up the greateſt part of the forenoon.</p>
            <p>That about ten of the clock, the Serjeant came and informed the Speaker that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was there ready, if he pleaſed to have him called in; the Speaker made anſwer (according to the uſual cuſtom) that as ſoon as the buſineſs then in Debate was at an end he would put
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170632:6"/> the Houſe in mind thereof, that ſo Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> might be called in.</p>
            <p>I then obſerving that the preſent Debate, in which the Houſe was then engaged, was like to laſt for half an hour, or more, out of my real and hearty reſpects to Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> and his welfare, went out of the Houſe on purpoſe to ſit with him and keep him company, reſolving to ſpend that time in giving him my beſt advice and councel, to prevent (if it might be) his utter ruine.</p>
            <p>But coming forth to the Lobby without the Parliament door, where uſually all perſons are placed, who either are brought or ſent to appear before the Houſe of Parliament, expecting to find Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> there, but miſſing of him, I returned back into the Houſe to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant, to be directed by him where Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Serjeant at Arms ſaid to me, come along with me, and I will bring you to the place where Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> is; and accordingly the Serjeant brought me to that little room mentioned in his Remonſtrance, upon the head of the ſtairs, a place that I never ſaw before, or ever heard of and there I found Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſitting by himſelf, with a Tobacco-Pipe in his hand, and a candle burning by him: What Mr Serjeant (ſaid I) is this little Cell to which you bring me: This is, ſaid the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant, my own Retiring Quarter, where I have alwayes two or three bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of good Wine to refreſh my ſelf, and all accommodations, as Tobacco, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to welcome my friends, if there ſhould be occaſion: And thereupon the Serjeant very nobly offered Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and my ſelf the ſaid entertainment; which done, the Serjeant departed to attend the ſervice of the Houſe, promiſing me, that aſſoon as the Debate of the Houſe grew to a concluſion, he would come and give me notice thereof, that ſo I might return to the Houſe when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was called in.</p>
            <p>Now when the Serjeant was departed, and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and my ſelfe alone together in this ſaid little room, out of my real and hearty care of his welfare, I did moſt ſeriouſly and earneſtly preſs him to be well adviſed of what he ſaid or did when he came to the Barr of the Parliament Houſe: For, ſaid I, if your carriage here, ſhould be like that at Gold-Smiths Hall, you will be undone for ever; and much to this purpoſe I ſpake then to him. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> gave me the hearing, but reply'd very little, only ſometimes when I was earneſt with him to ſubmit and conform, he would reply. Come, come, trouble not your ſelf, I ſhall do and ſay (when I come into the Houſe) what I ſhall think to be moſt fit. And when I had there even tired my ſelf in giving him my moſt earneſt and importunate advice, and had preſſed him to ſubmit and conform, wherein I ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half an hour; the Serjeant came and gave me notice that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Debate in the Houſe was drawing to a concluſion; and therefore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed me to come away; Riſing then to depart, I ſaid to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> be not, I pray you, ſo wilfull and obſtinate as to deſtroy your ſelf and your whole Poſterity, but hearken to the friendly advice that I have given you; and with that I was ſtept one foot without the door of the ſaid little room, going away, at which time Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ariſing out of his place, and coming towards the door after me, ſaid, I pray what is that good advice that you do give me! To whom I reply'd, When you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170632:6"/> come to the Barr of the Houſe of Parliament, do you there acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your miſcarriage at Goldſmiths Hall, and pray the pardon of the Houſe, and deſire that you may be remitted to Goldſmiths Hall, there to make your Compoſition according to the Articles of <hi>Exceter.</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> replyed, Is that your advice? I like it not; for, were I willing, yet I am altogether unable to pay the money of a Compoſition, for I have no money to pay it, but am alread indebted, therefore your advice is not ſeaſonable and good. Fy, fy, what mean you Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> replyed I, do not you know that I am very well acquainted with many Gentlemen whoſe debts are great, and the incumbrances up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eſtates very many, who pay for their Compoſitions, ſome three years value, ſome five, and yet they make a ſhift either by morgaging or ſelling, to ſave a part, rather then loſe the whole; and you, ſaid I, have lately bought a Farm in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> which is an addition to your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate at <hi>Awbery;</hi> and (as you told me your ſelf) coſt you between eight and ten thouſand pound; tis but the ſelling again of that Farm, and your Compoſition is paid, and all the reſt of your Eſtate ſaved. Well, well, ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> all your advice tends to this, That I ſhould ſell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way part of my Lands: No, replyed I, my advice is, that you ſhould ſubmit unto a Compoſition, and ſave your ſelf and your Eſtate from ruine; and ſo I departed from him into the Houſe of Parliament, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake with him more untill about four or five daies after, when I was ſent for to viſit him at <hi>Newgate:</hi> And by what means <hi>I</hi> came to <hi>Newgate</hi> and the paſſages between him and my ſelf, doth follow in my Anſwer to the next Charge mentioned in the 30. page.</p>
            <p>Reader, thou mayeſt obſerve that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in his relation of the matter, doth acknowledg that in all my diſcourſe, <hi>I</hi> did ſeem to condole his deplorable condition; and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> thought then that I did really, and not ſeemingly compaſſionate him, as will appear by what paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us four or five dayes after at Newgate. It was alwayes the ſtudy and endeavor of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> to gain himſelf the repute of a wiſe, ſtout, and prudent Gentleman: and ſo no doubt he thought himſelf to be, when he could laugh at the indiſcretions of all thoſe that made their compoſitions; whilſt he did with a ſtrong Faith, behold at a very remote diſtance, the King reſtoring him to his Eſtate without money, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a liberal reward for his great ſufferings, in juſtifying and owning his Cauſe beyond any other of his party: and I do believe, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> having through his pride and obſtinacy loſt that his reputation, in the judgement of the world, is therewith as much troubled as at the loſs of his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>But now Reader, thou art here deſired by that which followeth, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the wiſdome and prudence of this Gentleman.</p>
            <p>Whereas in the former relation; mentioned in page 28. unto which I have given an Anſwer: Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> might ſuppoſe when he pen'd that invention and contrived fiction, that his bare affirmation thereof might beget credit with thoſe that read the ſame, thinking that I could make no reply thereto, but a plain denial; becauſe the diſcourſe was in private betwixt us two.</p>
            <p>But here in his ſecond relation (a choice invention) ſet down in page 30 and 31. a relation wherein truth is not found in any one line; in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170632:7"/> penning whereof Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi>'s own conſcience and reaſon could tell him, not onely, that the things there related were untruths, but that I had ſeveral witneſſes to prove them ſo to be; and if ſo, then Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> great wiſdome and integrity, or rather ſomthing elſe is here to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, eſpecially ſince he hath engaged the faith of a Chriſtian, and honour of a Gentleman to make a true relation.</p>
            <p>Reader, If thou doſt ſeriouſly peruſe Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi>'s Relation, ſet down in page 30. and 31. to which I am now to give an Anſwer, thou wilt find there theſe three particulars much inſiſted on.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> meerly of his owne accord and officiouſneſs (nay if it be true that he received that ſharp reprehenſion, but four dayes before, from Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell)</hi> did moſt debaſedly, unſent for, reſort unto Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> then in Newgate, after he had been three or four daies in that priſon.</p>
            <p>And that he did then and there moſt earneſtly ſolicite him, that he might be imployed in doing Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſome further ſervice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did then reſolve to Petition the Parliament, that he might be admitted to his compoſition, and reſtored to his liberty; but Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> diſliked that Petition which he had drawen to that purpoſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it did expreſs that he had formerly ſubmitted to Compoſition, but was denied, for refuſing the Negative Oath and Covenant; and that Mr <hi>Aſhe</hi> perſwaded him to draw up a Petition in another Form, which he con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented unto; a Copy whereof is inſerted in page 31 of his Remonſtrance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did engage and promiſe Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to deliver that his Petition to the Parliament, and although Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> was often ſollicited, and minded of that his engagement and promiſe, yet to this day he never delivered the ſame.</p>
            <p>And here Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> might with as much truth have added, that which he did affirm at the High Court of Juſtice, where his expreſſion was to this effect,</p>
            <p>That in three or four dayes after he was committed to Newgate, he did draw an humble Petition to the Parliament, wherein he did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his miſcarriage, and deſired that he might be remitted to Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall, there to make his Compoſition; which Petition he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the care of Mr. <hi>Aſhe,</hi> (who called him Maſter, he noting thereby the intimacy and familiarity that was between us.) And Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did engage to deliver the ſame to the Parliament, but never performed his engagement; by which failer and breach of his truſt, Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> like <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed his Maſter.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe I anſwer and ſay, that there is not one word of truth in it, ſave onely that I was with Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in Newgate, about four dayes after the Parliament had committed him to that priſon; but I do deny that I came thither of my owne accord and unſent for, as Mr. <hi>Edward Aſhe,</hi> the Lady <hi>Stawell,</hi> and her waiting woman can and will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie.</p>
            <p>For thus it was, that upon the day before mentioned, the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> between 9 or 10 of the clock at night (when Mr. <hi>Edward Aſhe</hi> his gates were faſt ſhut, where I then lodged,) came thither, and deſired that the gates might be opened, that ſhe might be admitted to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe,</hi> and to deliver unto him a meſſage from Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell: Mr.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170632:7"/> 
               <hi>Edward Aſh</hi> did unwillingly permit his Gates to be opened at that time of the night; but becauſe the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> was a perſon of honour and worth, did aſſent thereunto.</p>
            <p>And when the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> came in, ſhe found me and Maſter <hi>Edward Aſhe</hi> in a little Parlor ſitting together, and ready to goe to bed.</p>
            <p>Then ſaid Maſter <hi>Edward Aſhe</hi> to the Lady, Madam, What bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs hath drawn you abroad ſo farre from your Lodging, at this time of the night? Sir, ſaid ſhe, I am ſent in a meſſage to your Brother, Mr. <hi>John Aſhe,</hi> from Mr. <hi>Stawell,</hi> my Husband, now in <hi>Newgate,</hi> who doth earneſtly deſire your Brother to come unto him preſently; for that, ſhe ſaid, Mr. <hi>Stawell</hi> hath a buſineſs of great concernment to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part unto him, which will not admit of any delay, but with the danger of his life. Mr. <hi>Edward Aſh</hi> then replyed, Madam, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall not, with my conſent, go forth of my houſe at this hour of the night, and I hope you conceive it not fitting, and ſo will he (my family and ſervants being all in the Countrey) and that it will not ſtand with my ſafety to keep my Gates unſhut, ſo long until my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall return home, in caſe he do go along with you to Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> as you deſire. And I did then tell the ſaid Lady, that it was a very unſeaſonable time, at that hour of the night, for me to go into a Priſon, and deſired her to excuſe me unto her Husband, letting him know, That I would be ready any hour the next day, to wait upon him, if he ſhould pleaſe to deſire it: But the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> continuing on in her importunate requeſt, and telling me, That in caſe I did not go with her, and ſpeak with her Husband, he would not reſt that night, nor would his mind be at quiet; and that he gave her in charge not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn until ſhe brought me along with her. The Lady with theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities at length prevailed with me, and I went with her to <hi>Newgate</hi> to ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> where he then lay.</p>
            <p>Now this being the very truth, as I have here related it, and what the Witneſſes aforenam'd can and will teſtifie, I do preſume, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Reader cannot believe, that I would at that unſeaſonable hour of the night go to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and there earneſtly ſollicite ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to imploy me in ſome new ſervice, when but four daies before, (if his relation in page 28 were true) with a ſevere reprehenſion he did caſhier me from his ſervice.</p>
            <p>But what was ſaid and done by me, and ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> that night at <hi>Newgate,</hi> is in the next place to be declared, and is as followeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my anſwer unto the ſecond particular contained in the 30 and 31 pages of the ſaid Remonſtrance.</p>
            <p>When I came to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> had directed me to her Husbands Lodging, I found ſir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſitting in a Chaire, taking a Pipe of Tobacco, who ſaid to me, <hi>You are welcome; this is done like a friend indeed, to viſit me in Priſon ſo late in the night;</hi> and then called his man to give me a ſtool to ſit down by him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted me to accompany him in taking a Pipe of Tobacco; I told him that I underſtood by his Lady, that he had a buſineſs of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to impart unto me, and therefore had ſent for me: I deſired
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170632:8"/> him, in regard it was very late, That he would let me know his buſineſs, becauſe I had engaged to my Brother in <hi>Fanchurch ſtreet,</hi> to return home unto him ſpeedily. Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſtill preſſed me, firſt to take ſome Tobacco, ſaying, <hi>It was not then much paſt ten of the Clock, and his cuſtom was, not to go to Bed before one or two in the morning.</hi> The Lady <hi>Stawell,</hi> then ſtanding by, ſaid, <hi>I pray Mr.</hi> Stawell <hi>impart unto Mr.</hi> Aſhe <hi>what you have to ſay unto him, for which you cauſed me to bring him hither: For I have engaged to Mr.</hi> Edward Aſhe, <hi>that his Brother ſhall not be detained here by you above half an hour at the moſt.</hi> Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> hereupon cauſed the ſervants, then preſent, to depart the Room, and there was only left with me, himſelf and his Lady. Then ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſh, you know very well in what houſes, and in what manner I have lived all my life time; and now ſee into what a noiſom and little ugly Chamber I am put into There,</hi> ſaid he, (pointing to one ſide of the Chamber) <hi>is a Trunk, through which paſſeth the filth of the upper Priſon; and under my Chamber is the Vault, into which all the filth of the Priſon is emptied; by means whereof I am an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed with ſuch a noiſom ſtink, the weather being hot, that it is impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me to endure it for any time without the danger of my life: Wherefore you being my only faithfull friend, upon whom I can relie, did think fit to ſend to you for my relief; and therefore do now entreat you, That either by a Motion, or upon a ſhort Petition, you would procure leave from the Parliament, that I may be removed to another Priſon, where I may enjoy the benefit of the open air, and ſome wholſome walk; and if upon your Motion, or the delivery of my Petition, you nominate the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>though it be a very chargeable place, I am contented, rather to be placed there, then to loſe my life in this ſtinking Goal.</hi> I gave Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> then this anſwer, Sir, as I am moſt ready and willing to deliver to the Parliament, any Petition for you, that may tend to your good, ſo am I very unwilling to deliver that which may be for your hurt: For, ſaid I, the Parliament will make this conſtruction of your Petition, That you ſtand ſtill reſolved in you contempt of their power and Authority, and for that end, do only deſire health and ſtrength to carry you through the encounter; and therefore my advice is, and, as a faithfull friend I give you my Councel, That ſince you have a mind to preferr a Petition unto the Parliament, let it be ſuch a one, as may doe you good, and quite free you from this, and all other priſons. <hi>What Petition,</hi> ſaid Sir <hi>John St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>well, do you mean?</hi> A Petition, ſaid I, wherein you ſhould acknowledge all your miſcarriages, both at Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall, and at the Parliament, and crave pardon for the ſame, and let the Prayer of your Petition be, to be remitted to Goldſmiths Hall to make your Compoſition, and receive the benefit of <hi>Exceter</hi> Articles.</p>
            <p>To this advice of mine Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> gave this Anſwer, Sir, you know my reſolution, as to Compounding; and you know, as I have often told you, That if I had a mind to Compound, yet have I no money to pay the Compoſition; and therefore Sir, let me entreat you to deliver this ſhort Petition to the Parliament for my removal out of this Priſon, and therein you will do the part of a faithfull friend ſince it is for the ſaving of my life. You have, ſaid he, told me the danger of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170632:8"/> this Petition; ſo that if I ſuffer by it, it is my own fault, and none of yours.</p>
            <p>I did at laſt conſent (when I could not perſwade him to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) and did promiſe him to deliver this Petition unto the Parliament, ſo as he would draw it up in ſuch humble Language, as I might not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a reproof upon the delivery thereof, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ſend me a foul draught of that Petition the next day, that in caſe I did miſlike his expreſſions, I ſhould correct it; and I bad him good night, and left him.</p>
            <p>Reader, thou haſt here a faithfull, and an exact Narrative of what was ſaid and done by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and my ſelf, at that time, when I viſited him at <hi>Newgate,</hi> which if compared with what is ſet down by Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in his Remonſtrance, page the 30 and 31. is quite an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing; and thou maiſt clearly underſtand, that the Petition which he often mentioneth, and which I promiſed to deliver to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was not the Petition which he hath there Printed, nor a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his re-admiſſion to Compoſition at Goldſmiths Hall, as he told the High-Court of Juſtice, was it but a Petition onely for his removal from <hi>Newgate</hi> to a better Priſon, as will more plainly appear by what followeth.</p>
            <p>Upon the next day after, I was at <hi>Newgate,</hi> Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his promiſe, and I had a ſight of the foul draught of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he intended for me; but the Preamble was penned in ſuch high and unſeemly language, that I was enforced with my own Pen to correct the greateſt part of it, and ſo returned the ſame unto him again with my amendments, which he not liking, did the next day ſend me another Petition of his own drawing; but I diſliked that alſo, becauſe the language was ſuch, as did not become a Delinquent in his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to tender unto the Parliament; but at laſt, after ſeveral amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when I could not prevail, to have it drawn as well as I deſired, I took it as it was, and promiſed ſir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to take the firſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to preſent it to the Parliament; which promiſe I did faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully perform, and did for about ſixteen dayes together, (for ſo long and no longer, had I that Petition in my cuſtody) wait early and late to get a time to deliver the ſame unto the Parliament; but <hi>Michaelmas</hi> then drawing on, and my particular occaſions calling me home into the Countrey, for the ordering my affairs, and ſetling my Eſtate there, having been above four years abſent from thence by reaſon of the Warre; I thereupon ſent my Letter to ſir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> letting him know, That I could not gain a time as yet to deliver his Petition to the Parliament, although I had done my utmoſt endeavours therein, and that my occaſions did call me ſuddenly into the Countrey; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did deſire him to direct me into what hand I ſhould put his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whileſt I was abſent, which ſhould not be above three weeks at moſt.</p>
            <p>This Letter I ſent to <hi>Newgate</hi> to ſir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and he returned me an anſwer to this effect, That he was very thankfull to me for the great care I had taken in the delivery of his Petition, and was ſorry that it had no better ſucceſſe; and that ſince my occaſions called me
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170632:9"/> into the Countrey, he directed me to place his Petition in the hands of Mr. <hi>Denzil Hollis,</hi> or Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton:</hi> the very next morning, I came to the Parliament-Houſe, ſomewhat early before the Houſe ſate, and there very happily I met Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> who was in a private diſcourſe with another Gentleman, I took the opportunity, becauſe I was to go out of Town the day following, and ſomewhat uncivilly interrupting Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> told him, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> preſented his reſpects un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and had ſent him a Petition, which he did deſire might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Houſe by his hand; Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> took from me the Petition, and put it in his pocket, willing me to acquaint Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> that he would take care thereof: And the ſame day, aſſoon as I did return unto my Lodging, I wrote a Letter to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> wherein I told him, That according to his direction, I had delivered his Petition to Mr <hi>Hollis,</hi> who had promiſed to take care thereof, and adviſed him to employ ſome friend to mind Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> of the ſame, leſt he ſhould forget it. Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> gave me an anſwer to this Letter the next morning, which Letter his ſervant delivered me as I was taking horſe to ride into the Countrey; The Contents of which Letter were, That he heartily thanked me for lodging his Petition in ſo worthy a hand, and that he would obſerve my advice, by ſending ſome friend to Mr. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> to mind him thereof, and ſo wiſhed me a happy journey, and a ſafe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <p>I then went into the Countrey, and returned again to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about three weeks after, and aſſoon as I met with Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> I asked him what he had done with Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Petition, which I had delivered him? he told me, That it was ſuch a Petition, that if he had delivered it to the Houſe, it would have more incenſed the Houſe againſt him: For in that Petition, ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> he deſired nothing of the Parliament, but his removal from <hi>Newgate,</hi> to a better Priſon. Then ſaid I, Where is the Petition? and what is become of it? Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> anſwered, That he had ſent it back to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> with this direction, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ſhould draw another Petition, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledging his miſcarriages, and to deſire pardon for the ſame, and the Prayer to be, That the Parliament would remit him to Gold-Smiths Hall, there to make his Compoſition, and receive the benefit of <hi>Exeter</hi> Articles. And I alſo ſent him word (ſaid he) that if he would ſend me ſuch a Petition, which would be for his good, I would not only deliver the ſame to the Parliament, but would engage all my friends, that his deſires might be granted.</p>
            <p>Well, ſaid I, did Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> hearken to your advice? and hath he ſent you ſuch a Petition? No, no, ſaid Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> he doth utterly refuſe to be adviſed by me: Certainly the man is either mad, or hath loſt his wits, elſe he would not be ſo obſtinate.</p>
            <p>Then ſaid I, Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> hath often been adviſed by me, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his friends to follow that courſe which you have now adviſed him unto: But he hath alwaies rejected our counſels, and is peremptory in his reſolutions, which will be his ruine. And I do affirm, that I never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any other Petition from Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> but that which I now mentioned.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170632:9"/>
            <p> And now Reader, having thus in all plainneſs and truth made thee this faithful Narrative, with all its circumſtances, and ſhewed who the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are that can (and I preſume will, if called) make good the ſame, thou wilt exceedingly admire the front and boldneſs of this Gentleman Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> who with ſo much confidence ſhould adventure to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in Print, that which not only his own conſcience tels him to be a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious untruth, but alſo knows the Witneſſes that can convict him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and what cauſe haſt thou then to believe thoſe other ſtories which he hath printed, and were, as they are pretended, private diſcourſes between Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I had here concluded this diſcourſe, but finding in page 59, 60, and 61. the Copy of a Letter ſigned by Sir <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> and directed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Thracy Paunsfoot</hi> Eſq and alſo a Certificate ſigned by Sir <hi>David Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> I thought it requiſite to give ſome anſwer to the ſaid Letter and Certificate, and then to conclude.</p>
            <p>In that Letter ſigned by Sir <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> amongſt other things which he doth there miſrecite, theſe particulars are related and aſſerted <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> deportment to us of the Committee at that time (meaning at his ſecond appearance) and the other time that he was before us, for my part I took no offence at it, neither do I think juſtly there could be any: he is of himſelf of a blunt carriage, but for incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity I ſaw none at the times he was before us, either in geſture or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; for my part I would have had him admitted to Compoſition, knowing money would have done the Parliament ſervice; beſides, by his Articles we ought; but I was but one, others were not of my mind, but heightned his offence high, took acceptions at his carriage and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, would have it reported to the Houſe. For my part, then I thought that there was more in it than was outwardly expreſſed; but the truth was, by the Order of the Houſe, we were bound up from admitting him to compound, unleſs he took the Covenant, except the Houſe would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence with it, which they did when they approved of thoſe Articles.</p>
            <p>To this part of the Letter I give this Anſwer, That Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> was the principal man of all the Committee that took exceptions at the Paper which he is pleaſed now to call Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> Petition, and was preſented at his firſt appearance: And he firſt moved, That the ſaid Paper might be rejected, ſaying, it was rather a Remonſtrance then a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. And Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> eſpecially, together with all the reſt of the Committee then preſent, were ſo offended at Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> language and behaviour, that they made an Order that I (then being in the Chair of that Committee) ſhould the next day report the ſame to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which Report had been made accordingly, but that I my ſelf (out of my reſpects to Sir <hi>John Stawell)</hi> did prevail with the Committee to ſuſpend that their Order for a time; and alſo obtained for him this favor, That three or four daies time for conſideration was given him, in which time he might amend his Petition, and therewith bring a particular of his Eſtate under his hand, upon which the Committee might proceed to perfect his Compoſition; This favour I ſay again, was procured from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170632:10"/> the Committee only by my mediation, much againſt the mind of Sir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Irby,</hi> who preſſed the Report forthwith to be made.</p>
            <p>And Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> at his ſecond appearance before the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall, carrying himſelf with the like inſolency, and giving the ſame language (if not worſe) than he did at the firſt: Sir <hi>Anthony Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> principally taking offence thereat, did, with the reſt of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee then preſent, order Mr. <hi>Iohn Stephens</hi> (then Chairman) to report the ſame to the Parliament. All which in effect I did affirm unto Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> upon Thurſday the 23 of <hi>November</hi> laſt, before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Parliament ſitting in the Starr Chamber, by whom Sir <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Irby</hi> had been examined, as a Witneſs for Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> and his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations are in effect the ſame as is contained in this Letter.</p>
            <p>Which Examinations being there read in the preſence of the ſaid Sir <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> I did move the Committee to ask him two or three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, which being granted, were as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether he was preſent at the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall the firſt and ſecond time when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> appeared there.</p>
            <p>He anſwered, <hi>He was then preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall (taking offence at Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> language and misbehaviour there) did order Mr. <hi>John Stephens</hi> to Report the ſame to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>He anſwered, <hi>Yes, that Order was then made by the Committee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether to the making of the ſaid Order for Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> to Report as aforeſaid, he (Sir <hi>Anthony Irby)</hi> did give his conſent and his Vote in the affirmative for the ſame.</p>
            <p>He anſwered, <hi>Yes, he did, for there was no Member of the ſaid Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee that gave a Nagative to the ſaid Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the Anſwer to this third Queſtion, Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> made ſome pauſe, and it ſtuck ſome time with him, becauſe he knew it did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict what he had ſaid before in the juſtification of Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> good language and fair deportment.</p>
            <p>In the next place Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> in his Letter ſaith.</p>
            <p>That the Committee was bound up by an Order of the Houſe to put Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to take the Covenant and Negative Oath, before he was admitted to Compoſition, but that Order the Houſe did ſuſpend when they approved of the Articles of <hi>Exceter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> might have written the whole truth, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced the ſame if he had been ſo pleaſed; for he knew, that by an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of both Houſes of Parliament, the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall were bound up not to admit any Delinquent to his Compoſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had taken the Covenant and Negative Oath, and that by the ſaid Ordinance, they mere impowered to commit the Delinquent ſo refuſing to Priſon, untill he ſhould do the ſame. And Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> doth know that the Houſe of Lords had not then approved of the ſaid Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, but refuſed the ſame, and therefore the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall were ſtill bound by the ſaid Ordinance to do as aforeſaid, and that the ſame Ordinance was not ſuſpended, as Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> pretends: But Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> in his ſaid Letter, doth yet proceed further <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince (I muſt confeſs) I have heard from ſome of the then Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament, that one of our Society would have bought a Manor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170632:10"/> of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> that lay near him, but I knew nothing of it then, but took notice of ſome tartneſs in the party, which being neighbours and Countreymen, I ſomething wondred at, thinking that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> might have exaſperated him by ſome action in the time of Warr.</p>
            <p>Reader, I pray obſerve here, that Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> doth not name the perſon who would have bought this Manor of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> nor doth he name thoſe Members of Parliament that told him this ſtory, nor the time when this was told him. But in his examination lately taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Committee of Parliament, he doth there ſet forth, that the time when he heard this ſtory, was about two years ſince, when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> was brought before the High Court of Juſtice, and that the Member that told it him, was Sir <hi>Edward Baynton,</hi> as they two ſate together in Sir <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham Williams</hi> his Houſe, and that I my ſelf was the perſon of our ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety that would have bought the ſaid Manor.</p>
            <p>Where note, that when Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> at the High Court of Juſtice had publiſhed this ſcandalous fiction, which coming to the knowledge of Sir <hi>Edward Baynton,</hi> he tels it to Sir <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> and now Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> doth make uſe of this ſtory in this his Letter, thereby to induce the Reader the better to believe what he hath written in the juſtification of Sir <hi>John Stawell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſcandalous fiction was never heard of or told by Sir <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> till about ſeven years after that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> had been at the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall.</p>
            <p>And obſerve likewiſe, that Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> ſaith, it was a Manor that I would have bought of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and that it lay near me; when as Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> tels you it was a Farm, and it lay at <hi>Aubery,</hi> which is above ſixteen miles from my dwelling, and I have no Land near the place.</p>
            <p>But Sir <hi>Anthony Irby's</hi> memory muſt be blamed, that hath here failed him, according to the common lot of thoſe which contrive and invent ſuch like fictions.</p>
            <p>As for the Certificate ſigned by Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> wherein he ſaith, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came to the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall, with a fair and civil reſpect, and preſented his Petition within the time limited by the Articles of <hi>Exceter, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where obſerve, That Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> and Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> do give the ſelf-ſame evidence, as to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> fair and civil deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall; but Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> as well as Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> did give his vote in the affirmative, that Mr. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> ſhould report to the Parliament the inſolent language and ill beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> before the ſaid Committee; for ſaith Sir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Irby,</hi> every Member then at the ſaid Committee conſented to the ſaid Order, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> miſcarriage there ſhould be reported to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble my ſelf nor the Reader with any more of this old Gentlemans Certificate; for the time when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came to Goldſmiths Hall, was in the heat of Summer, and it is very likely that the good old man was then nodding, and ſo could not mind what the Committee and himſelf did, or it may be his memory through age doth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170632:11"/> fail him, for it is now about eight years ſince that theſe tranſactions were at Goldſmiths Hall.</p>
            <p>It might be expected that I ſhould give ſome anſwer to that aſpertion which Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath caſt upon me and Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> in the firſt Paragraph of p. 26. of his Remonſtrance, where he ſeems to inſinuate, and would make the Reader believe that the Report which Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> made to the Parliament of his inſolent behaviour before the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall, was no other but what Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> had received from me, and that I had inſtructed him what to ſay; and why? Mark Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> reaſon for this inſinuation, Becauſe ſaith he, The Report which Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> made to the Parliament, is the ſame with Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony given at the High Court of Juſtice, and therefore Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> took his Report from Mr. <hi>Aſhe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a notorious untruth, and an idle aſpertion, caſt both upon Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> and my ſelf; for Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> did report no other thing to the Parliament touching ſir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> ill behaviour, but what he heard come forth of his own mouth, which was ſo much as gave Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> occaſion to ſay in the cloſe of his Report to the Houſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if the Parliament did not make Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>a Traitor, Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>had made them Traitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Reader, after a long forbearance, and not without ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs, have I given thee a rude, yet a moſt true and faithfull Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all that paſſed between Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and my ſelf, in relation to thoſe ſcandals, which in the Pamphlet, Entituled, his <hi>Humble Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance,</hi> are moſt malitiouſly inſinuated: I could have added much more, if I was not unwilling, either to tire thy patience, or to recriminate, or to aggravate his ingratitude towards me; but by what I have written, thou maiſt clearly perceive how injuriouſly he hath charged me with the ſin of Coveting the Goods of my neighbour, and conſequently with the breach of all the Commandments: And I could wiſh that I had not juſt cauſe (were I minded ſo to do) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quere who it was that coveted</hi> Mrs Baſſets <hi>Lands, and got it by a Cheat.</hi>
               </note> to retort the ſame crime in a high nature on himſelf: and to deſire him ſeriouſly to lay it to heart, and conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even that offence of his, be not one cauſe why it hath pleaſed God ſo to harden his heart, that he ſhould contemn the Parliaments mercy, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ſubmit unto a Compoſition according to the Articles of <hi>Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> by which means he hath been moſt juſtly deprived of his whole Eſtate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170632:11"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees of his Highneſs moſt Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Councel, in the Cauſe between Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and the Purchaſers.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The Petition of</hi> William Lawrence <hi>of</hi> Edenburgh, <hi>Eſq</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat whereas your Petitioner is imployed in his Highneſs ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which requires his perſonal attendance there; and he being one of the ſaid Purchaſers, as he is informed, the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in his abſence, without ſummons or other legal notice, hath, and doth endeavour by ſurprize to purſue your Petitioner, and work divers things againſt him prejudicial to his right. And whereas your Petitioners purchaſe was before he left <hi>England,</hi> confirmed by Act of Parliament, and in confidence thereof, your Petitioner ſuſpending nothing, left no proviſion nor order againſt any ſuits, not doubting the ſame. And your Petitionr in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition he is in, is now deprived of all Councel, intelligence, Agents writings, evidences, proofs, and other things neceſſary to maintain a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and of all fit means to make uſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Petitioner therefore humbly prayeth that no proceedings be ſuffered againſt him otherwiſe then is by Law allowable againſt a perſon not ſummoned, and out of the Nation, and who hath beſides the warrant of an Act of Parliament, which if permitted to be queſtioned, there can be no end of controverſie. And that for the farther ſecurity of your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner the preſent Petitiin and Reaſons annexed, may be read or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and reſt the with papers of other Purchaſers before your honors miſinformation from the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <head>
               <hi>Reaſons that the Petitioners purchaſe ought not to be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Sir</hi> John Stawell.</head>
            <p n="1">I. Your Petitioner ſaith that ſuch members of the Committee of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as have acted for the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> againſt Purchaſers, are parties, and not Judges, and their orders and certificates ought to have no credit or authority. And your Petitioner ſaith they have miſtated the Caſe, tranſgreſſed the duty of an inferiour juriſdiction, and preſumed on Acts of Soveraign power, they have wrongfully indebted the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in vaſt ſums of mony to the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> they have occaſioned falſe ſcandal on it of infringing his Articles, and have not been
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170632:12"/> indifferent or equal in their proceedings, either as to publike or private rights, all which your Petitioner will be ready to prove.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Your Petitioner ſaith, that divers Purchaſers, ſome through fear, and others by conſpiracy with the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> have, and do put in divers feigned and feeble Petitions and pleas, part of which the ſaid S. <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to delude the vulgar, hath put in print, and the ſame purchaſers have and do endeavour to betray the Cauſe of the Commonwealth, and their companions; your Petitioner therefore deſireth that no proceeding be made againſt him in groſs, but his cauſe heard patiently and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Your Petitioner ſaith, that hath been already decided and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Parliament, that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath forfeited his Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. And thereupon the Act of ſale of his Eſtate was made, and that judgement being given by Parliament, to whoſe proceedings Purchaſers neither could nor ought to be privy, and ſo much time ſince paſt, That though the evidence and proofs were then never ſo clear, yet the memory may be now loſt; the Members Witneſſes proofs dead, removed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, or taken off. It would be unreaſonable to put Purchaſers now to prove over again, what hath been adjudged, and would not only queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells,</hi> but moſt part of all the lands, the Parliament ever ſold or ſhall ſell.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Your Petitioner ſaith, notwithſtanding that if he ſhall be inforced, he will prove that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> never ſubmitted to Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to Articles, and that he hath both omitted and committed divers Acts then, and ſince, which have clearly forfeited them.</p>
            <p n="5">V. There is ſufficient publickly and vulgarly known of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> as none needs admire at the judgment paſſed againſt him; for he offered nothing but inſolencies and affronts to the Parliament it ſelf, when brought before them, he reviled the Committe for compounding, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be Delinquents themſelves: He charged the Judges at the Upper Bench that they ſate by a counterfeit Sale, and that they were mock Judges, and the Jury a pack of Knaves; he openly denied and defied the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream authority, and charged the Court and Attorney-General with high Treaſon for acting by it, publickly, and to their faces. He declared for the Scots in Arms againſt this Commonwealth, and till all was loſt; he made only a ſhew and pretence to deſire to compound, but really reſolved and declared againſt it, and derided and ſcorned all thoſe who ſubmitted to it. All which was beſides many others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. No fit language or behaviour to demand a Compoſition with.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A breach of the Peace within the Parliaments quarters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An incenſing of the People to rebel, and adhere to the enemy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The higheſt prejudice to the Parliaments quarters a priſoner could do, though he knew by his Articles he was not to prejudice the ſame, and had given ſecurity to that end.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Divers of the ſame Acts have been made treaſonable by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If any innocent perſon had preſumed on half ſo much it had been his ruine,</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> refuſed to acknowledge himſelf a Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and thereby willfully refuſed his Compoſition.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170632:12"/> 1. It was the command of the Parliament, and the Commiſſioners for compounding could not juſtifie compoſition on any other terms.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Houſe of Lords being part of the Parliament, had not then confirmed his Articles.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Parliament had conſiderately deſigned that all Delinquency ſhould rema in of Record, that both in the diſpoſing of Offices of truſt and power, and other future Acts relating to the Commonwealth, they might the more readily guide themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A diſhonour might have been aſperſed upon them, that it had been <hi>Latrocinium,</hi> and not <hi>Bellum,</hi> a robbery, and no juſt War, if together with the penalties, a confeſſion or tryal of the offence had not likewiſe appeared.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Both Commiſſioners and Sequeſtrators might have been otherwiſe liable to future actions and ſuits from the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> and his heirs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Parliament had appointed other Courts, as namely the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Appeals, and thoſe of the Common-Law for relief of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſequeſtred, being not Delinquents, which were open unto him for trial, if he would ſtand on that point; but by ſtanding on it with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for compounding, 'tis clear heouſted them of juriſdiction to meddle with him.</p>
            <p n="7">7. His refuſal was not out of error or miſtake, but adviſedly, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately, and after he was told of it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Both before, and at time of making his Articles, it was known that by the uſual courſe of ſubmitting to compoſition; the firſt point was acknowledgement of Delinquency, and therefore if the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> had not liked it, he might have choſen whether he would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Articles without an expreſs diſpenſation of that very point.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Your Petitioner ſaith that the intereſt of the land in queſtion doth not totally belong to the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> but there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers charges upon it, and divers tranſactions have been made touching the ſame to other perſons, making no pretence to Articles, who never made claim, and therefore bound by the ſale which your Petitioner ought to have liberty to examin, as well by the Oath of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> as other perſons, and to have a Production of the Deeds, Titles, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of the ſaid land in Court, if there be cauſe.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Your Petitioner ſaith, that Purchaſers were commanded to pay in their ſecond moyeties by Act of Councel at White-Hall, and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates were thereupon confirmed by Act of Parliament called by his Highneſs, which is the deepeſt fundamental of property can be laid, and the higheſt aſſurance the Law can give, and ought not to be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. His Highneſs hath been pleaſed likewiſe by his Oath in the Iw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument Government, to confirm the ſecuring property, and to Govern therein according to the Laws and Statutes, the benefit whereof your Petitioner doth claim.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Your Petitioner acknowledgeth Laws may be repeal'd, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments reverſed, and Authorities countermanded, but humbly ſaith, That buying and ſelling binds Supream Power it ſelf: And that in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſale the full price, both of money and blood hath been received. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170632:13"/> therefore neither God nor man can revoke their onwn bargain and ſales; and the whole Chriſtian Religion it ſelf hath no other foundation but a bargain and ſale.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Your Petitioner ſaith, his Purchaſe being a reverſion, he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to drown and extinguiſh his old Leaſe, for which old Leaſe the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> received of this Petitioners father far more then the whole Inheritance was worth. And your Petitioners occaſions have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſince his Purchaſe compell'd him to commit acts of forfeiture of his ſaid old Leaſe by Feoffments, and otherwiſe, and to charge the mixt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of old and new Purchaſe, part with a joynture, part in tail to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, part with debts, part orphans money, part others. And upon ſuch tranſacting and charging, the ſame hath bound himſelf in many penal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venats, and Bonds, to warranty, ſo that if Juſtice be not done to your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner in maintenance of his Right, your Petitioner is utterly deſtroyed and made incapable of other Indempnity or Reparation.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Your Petitioner was totally ignorant of the Articles of <hi>Exceter,</hi> or any pretence of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to the ſame, and the ſame Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> might and ought to have given him notice of the ſame, and was earneſtly requeſted and ſolicited to give your Petitioner notice and directions of his deſires touching his intended purchaſe. And the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did notwithſtanding purpoſely and fraudulently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceàl the ſame from your Petitioner; which point, though your Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had nothing elſe to ſay, is unanſwerable both in the laws of peace and war.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. Your Petitioner ſaith, that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> might, and ought further to have given notice to the Truſtees for ſale, the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of obſtructions, the Terretenants of the land, who had preemption, as it is the courſe, and other perſons have done, though inacted to be ſold, and their claims taken away; as the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel's</hi> was, but he did not; and therefore by his own wilfull defaults he loſt the benefit of ſtopping ſales, which others in the like condition obtained.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioner ſaith, that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> is a ſubject, and the Land in queſtion Engliſh Land, and the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> neither doth nor can claim by his Articles to be in better condition then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the Subjects of <hi>England.</hi> And they, if their Eſtates happen to be ſold by miſtake in Parliament, or erroneus Judgement at Common-Law, or their claims have been unjuſtly refuſed, or there be a truſt or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Equity in Chancery on the Land, whereof Purchaſers have no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, muſt take in lieu thereof that expedient which the Law allows, namely, reparation in value as far as is proper. And for the reſidue, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by way of Action, which legal expedient is made good by the ſaid Articles, and without them he can have no benefit of the ſame.</p>
            <p>By the Act for ſettlement of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Parliament declared in a far ſtronger caſe, and though no ſale were made to neceſſitate it; that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons there might be tranſplanted from their own Eſtates of equal value, notwithſtanding they had been adjudged comprized within Articles.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> himſelf hath meaſured the ſame, and far worſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to others; for the whole Pariſh of <hi>Cothelſtone</hi> in <hi>Somerſet</hi> hath been by him miſerably and totally depopulated. And not awaiting the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring of their Eſtates, he by force, fraude, and terror expelled them, their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170632:13"/> wives, children and families to ſwim through their own tears to new Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Here therefore as the Law warrants, and neceſſity commands, ſo the Finger of God ſeems to direct, and Juſtice it ſelf to cry aloud for retaliation.</p>
            <p>It would be a very great cruelty and injuſtice by not making good pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſales to ſacrifice to his rage and revenge all the well-affected people of fifteen or ſixteen great Mannors, who have incurred his hatred meerly out of ſervice to the publick, and have the faith and honour, both of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and civil power engaged to protect them: which if not performed unto them, he will in point of Eſtate neither give quarter to man, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or child, but will totally extirpate and deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> himſelf is in no ſuch caſe as he pretends: For as your Petitioner is informed, his principal place of Reſidence being a magnificent ſeat, is purchaſed by his Lady for his uſe; and beſides he hath left him unſold and purchaſed by his Ladies aſſigns, and friends, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred pounds <hi>per annum</hi> more. And if he hath the reſidue of his Rents filled up with Rents of State-Land, the money whereof is as good as his own, he hath nothing to object but that he ſcorns the title, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires only to deal in Merchandize will ſwim beſt if the ſhip of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth and Government ſink together. But certainly cannot ſay, but as touching his poor depopulated Tenants, whom he pull'd out like ſnails from their only houſes, to which their lives were tied. But he is far better dealt, then he dealt with them, or intends to deal with the reſidue, if ever delivered into his hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170632:14"/>
            <head>REASONS FOR <hi>ESTABLISHMENT OF PUBLIKE SALE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly tendered, as well in behalf of the Common-wealth, as likewiſe of the Purchaſers of the Eſtate of Sir</hi> Iohn Stawell, <hi>and all others, who upon the Warrant and Authority of an Act of Parliament, and in ſervice thereto have not onely engaged their Eſtates and money, but the price and blood of themſelves and neareſt Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. TT is an abſolute maxime, that no power can be of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance unleſs founded on the title of Land, and that founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be laid without credit to ſell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. One Preſident of Revocation, will make the credit of the State ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, none will buy or fell with it; For once forſworn, ever for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This will deſtroy the being of Souldiery, by making all got by the ſword unſeaſonable; neither can the ſpoils and Conqueſts, though of the whole world, be of uſe, if not vendible; but then the more victories, the poorer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is no other permanent Bar againſt the King of the Scots, but ſales of land; and to deſtroy theſe will reduce him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If Articles may reverſe ſales, by the ſame juſtice ought perjury in Witneſſes, injuſtice in Judges, abſence of Witneſſes or Parties at time of their trial, new Diſcoveries ſince, and infinite others, which principle will make queſtionable, or deſtroy all Sales ever made or to be made, and leave the Parliament no power at all to warrant any.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Reverſing Sales will make the Enemie potent and formidable, and Friend poor and deſpicable.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Friend loſt, and Enemy not got, but made more fit for diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and dangerouſneſs, neither is there any way to aſſure them, but tranſplanting to other lands on the Parliaments title.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To unfreeze an Enemy, and be ſtung to death, is folly, not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Touching Grants by Act of Parliament, neceſſity and the Law of the Land frees them from being avoided by any errour of Fact, Law, or Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty preceding.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Otherwiſe no Enemy could or would Article, Truce or League with the Parliament, for fear of inviſible errour and preincumbrance on their Acts, and want of power to warrant them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such a principle may not onely deſtroy all Articles in general, but doth part icularly thoſe of <hi>Exceter:</hi> For at the beginning of the wars, all adherers to the Parliament, were promiſed indemnity therein, againſt the Delinquent and his party; which very Indemnity is clean contrary ſince by thoſe Articles granted the Delinquent againſt them; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170632:14"/> any ceremony or hearing of thoſe innocent adherers to their friends, who had loſt their lives and eſtates in the ſervice: And it cannot therefore be reaſon or juſtice to allow the Delinquent to diſannul the Act of Sale by a pre-promiſe of indemnity in Articles, and not to allow thoſe Innocents to avoid his Act of Articles by thoſe pre-promiſes of indemnity to them at the beginning of the wars.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All Acts of indemnity to their owne Souldiery might be avoided, by admitting Reviews for error or equity preceding.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All ancient Parliament laws, and <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf may be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on that ground.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As to Eſtates and Titles, if an Act of Parliament ſhall not be a <hi>Non ultra</hi> of Controverſies, the liberty of the people is deſtroyed; and there is no Free-hold in <hi>England,</hi> but all Tenants at will.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is in vain in the regulation of the Law, to free inferiour tranſactions from ſecret pre-incumbrances, if the Supream are liable to the ſame, or worſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10. It is unjuſt if Acts of Sale ſhould be binding to innocents, and not to Delinquents: what a ſhame would it be if our Laws ſhould be cords to one, and cob-webs to the other?</p>
            <p n="11">11. It is unjuſt to prefer a pure promiſe before property; For <hi>Rem Domino vel non Domino vendente duobus; In jure eſt potior traditione prior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Quod fieri non debet factum valet.</hi> If an Inheretrix happen to be married, or Inheritance ſold, though contrary to Articles; it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to perform thoſe Articles by committing adultery or robbery, for that were to do evil that good might com thereby: But there is an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and juſt way left to perform them, which is reſtitution in value, and may be more honourable too then <hi>ſpecie,</hi> for value may be ſevenfold if Parties pleaſe; But <hi>ſpecie</hi> can be but ſingle.</p>
            <p n="13">13. It is a known Rule, if Covenants happen by matter <hi>ex poſt facto</hi> to be either impoſſible in themſelves, injuſt as to third perſons, contrary to the Laws, or inconſiſtent with publick ſafety. It is unlawful to perform them otherwiſe then in value.</p>
            <p n="14">14. No ſupream power ought to repeal their own Bargains and Sales, though they may their laws, for <hi>Regum Contractus non ſunt leges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. By the very words of the Articles of <hi>Exceter,</hi> a Delinquent nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth nor can claim to be in better condition then the reſidue of the ſubjects of <hi>England.</hi> And they if their Eſtates happen to be ſold by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of authority, either by a miſtake in Parliament, or erroneous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Common-Law; or if they have a Title to a Truſt or Equity in <hi>Chancery,</hi> whereof Purchaſers have no notice, they muſt loſe it, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with ſuch recompence in value as the Law allows; what an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation would it be if two meaſures of juſtice ſhould be kept, a greater for the Enemy, and a ſmaller for the Subject.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Caſe in point is reſolved and practiſed to the ſubjects of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> yet have they as good Articles as thoſe of <hi>Exceter,</hi> as appears by the Act for ſetling <hi>Ireland,</hi> dated 12 <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1652. in the tenth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and laſt Proviſo; for it is expreſly enacted, <hi>That they may be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted from their own Eſtates to remote Eſtate of like value, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have been adjudged compriſed within Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170632:15"/> 17. Purchaſers for the moſt part are undone, and incapable of Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Tenants having drowned and forfeited their Eſtates, Widows, Wives, Orphants, and Fatherleſs having yeilded up their portions; and the eſtate paſſed from hand to hand, to ſo many manner of conveyances, uſes, truſts and croſe Covenants, as is impoſſible to reconcile or accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate with any value; whereas the eſtate of the Delinquent is only the intereſt of a ſingle perſon, who can alledge no reaſon why to avoid all theſe inconveniencies, he ſhould not accept an eſtate equal or better then his own in value; But only that he ſcorns to take land on the Title, either of Parliament or Army.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Touching Honour, it will reflect deeply on the Honour of the Parliament, to retract their own Sales; on the Honor of the Protector, himſelf being ſo eminently named, and made a party to the Act of Sale; on the Honour of the army, the people eſteeming publick Sales to be the military Market, and planting of the Sphear, where by the Laws of Nations all ought to have ſecurity and protection in dealing, and the rights of buying and ſelling to be obſerved inviolable. And the Honour of God not to juſtifie Delinquents to deſtroy Innocents.</p>
            <p>By all which it is hoped it will appear to all juſt and intelligent perſons, that to reverſe publick Sales of Delinquents Lands, made by Act of Parliament upon Articles or any cauſe preceding, whereof Purchaſers had no notice, is contrary to wiſdom, Juſtice, Honour, and the Laws of God and man.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170632:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reaſons why the Purchaſers of Sir</hi> John Stawels <hi>Eſtate, deſire the late Vote concerning the confirmation of the Purchaſes may be enacted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. A Great noiſe of terrour is ſpread amongſt the People by the proceeding of the Committee of Articles; and men ſtill remain fearful to bring in their money to the State, unleſs ſatisfied with an Act.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The preſumption of the Committee of Articles in thoſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the Reſolution of the late Parliament, was grounded meerly on this, <hi>That the ſame was a Vote, and not an Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Intervals of Parliaments, on the ſame grounds men of impudent ſpirits will ſleight a Vote not enacted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is uſual and equal for Sellers to do Acts of further aſſurance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Purchaſers are menaced and threatned they ſhall not hold quiet long what they have purchaſed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They ſhall not be able to ſell off their Purchaſes to others, but with great loſs.</p>
            <p n="7">7. An Act leaves Purchaſers in no other condition as againſt the State, then they were before, but onely is to ſecure them againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Many Acts of Parliament have been confirmed again by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though ſufficiently valid before, and particularly <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> though unqueſtionable in it ſelf, hath been confirmed above thirty ſeveral times.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170632:16"/>
            <head>Thurſday the thirteenth of <hi>October,</hi> 1653.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>An</hi> Act <hi>for confirmation of the Sale of the Lands and Eſtate of Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>Knight of the Bath.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BE it Enacted and declared by Authority of Parliament, That all Sales made of any Eſtate, Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Goods or Chattels of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the Bath, by vertue or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of any Act or Acts of Parliament, are hereby confirmed and eſtabliſhed: And accordingly all purchaſers and buyers of the ſame, ſhall and may have, hold, and quietly enjoy the ſame to them, their Heirs and Aſſignes, according to their reſpective intereſt and eſtates purchaſed or bought, and according to the Rules, Conditions, and Limitations pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the ſaid Acts, any Law or Judgement to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Scobell, Clerk Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170632:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
